Guide to the Jim Graham papers, 1961-2015 MS2013
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Jim Graham papers
1961-2015
1983-2014
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Graham, Jim
MS2013
80 Linear Feet
Records include personal files of Jim Graham from both his time as a member of the DC Council, as well as materials created during his early career and post-Council, and constitution and by-laws for Whitman-Walker Clinic, correspondence, financial records, photographs, videocassettes, audio cassette tapes, executive meeting minutes, annual reports and other publications of the Whitman-Walker Clinic, publications and materials of other AIDS-related organizations, scrapbooks, newspaper articles, brochures, conference publications, property information, posters, and buttons related to Whitman-Walker events.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Jim Graham in three accessions. One in 1999, one in 2007, and the most recent in 2015. Graham passed away in 2017 and his estate made a donation in 2018, which was incorporated into this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
James Graham (August 26, 1945 - June 11, 2017) served as a member of the Council of the District of Columbia, representing Ward One, from 1999 to 2015. While on the Council, he was known for revitalizing the Columbia Heights neighborhood and the U Street Corridor. He also worked to protect affordable housing and tenants' rights in Ward One. Graham served on a number of Committees and other organizations as part of his Council service. Notably, he was on the Board for the Washington Area Metropolitan Transportation Authority (WMATA). He won re-election three times in 2002, 2006, and 2010, but was defeated in the 2014 Primary by Brianne Nadeau.
Born in Scotland, Graham and his family immigrated to the United States when he was a child. He became a U.S. Citizen in his late teens. He attended the University of Michigan Law School, and later served as a clerk for Supreme Court Chief Justice Earl Warren. After Warren's death, he worked for the U.S. Senate Governmental Affairs Committee. Graham also was an instructor for at least two Washington, DC institutions—Georgetown University and George Washington University. He taught courses related to law and government.
Prior to his election to DC Council, he served as the Executive Director of the Whitman-Walker Clinic from 1984-1999. Much of the Clinic's success can be attributed to Graham's high-profile leadership and tireless advocacy. In 1998, Graham was appointed to a three-year term on the first Board of Trustees of the new George Washington University Hospital.
In addition to his service to the Whitman-Walker Clinic, Graham was a member of many other AIDS-affiliated organizations. Since 1983, he was a member of the D.C. AIDS Task Force, a member of the Board of Directors of the AIDS Action Council and the National Lesbian and Gay Health Foundation. His advocacy of AIDS research led to membership on the Coalition for Consumers Health and Safety, the Advisory Committee of the Washington AIDS Partnership, and the Advisory Board of Concerned Citizens on Alcohol and Drug Abuse, Inc., a project of the Greater Mt. Calvary Holy Church. He also held the positions of Treasurer and Board Member for the National AIDS Network.
Graham's work with AIDS took him to Poland and Thailand, as well as to numerous national and international conferences. In 1989, he was invited to Krakow, Poland to discuss the gay community's response to AIDS at an HIV conference sponsored by Project Hope, the World Health Organization, and the Polish Ministry of Health. In 1991, he traveled to Thailand where he was able to gain another glimpse at the international state of AIDS.
The mission of the Whitman-Walker Clinic is ".. .a non-profit community-based health organization serving the Washington, D.C. metropolitan region. Established by and for the gay and lesbian community, the clinic is comprised of diverse volunteers and staff who provide or facilitate the delivery of high quality, comprehensive, accessible health care and community services. Whitman-Walker Clinic is especially committed to ending the suffering of all those infected and affected by HIV/AIDS."
In 1973 five men, known as the Gay Men's Venereal Disease Task Force, organized in response to the growing number of sexually transmitted diseases affecting gay men. They formed the Gay Men's VD Clinic (GMVDC) and affiliated themselves with the Washington Free Clinic to provide a place where gay men could receive testing and treatment. The success of the clinic in meeting the needs of gay men prompted its leaders to expand the scope of their services to include a wider range of health care services for gay men and lesbians. The GMVDC separated from the Washington Free Clinic in 1977 and in 1978 the Whitman-Walker Clinic was officially created.
The Whitman-Walker Clinic was named after Dr. Mary Walker and poet Walt Whitman, two individuals who volunteered their services to care for the wounded during the American Civil War. The Clinic's intent was to continue the tradition of providing volunteer health care services to those in need. The official charter states that the goals of the Whitman-Walker Clinic are to establish, develop, and operate in the Washington, D.C. metropolitan area a nonprofit health service to promote the prevention and eradication of illnesses and diseases among gay people. The Clinic's first operating office was located at 1606 17th Street, NW. Over the next decade the services provided by the Whitman-Walker Clinic expanded in response to the growing needs of the gay community, and eventually to the needs of the larger society as a whole, as the AIDS epidemic spread throughout the general population.
In 1980, in response to growing financial difficulties the Clinic moved to a space on 18th Street in Adams Morgan. In 1987, the Whitman-Walker Clinic moved its location to a larger space on 14th and S Streets. The services it provided continued to grow, in particular into the areas of suburban Virginia and Maryland. The Whitman-Walker Clinic began to focus more on providing AIDS-related services and programs emphasizing education, prevention, and early testing for the HIV/AIDS virus were steadily developed as the Clinic moved into the 1990's. The Whitman-Walker Clinic has grown into one of the most respected AIDS service and gay and lesbian health organizations in the nation.
Jim Graham passed away due to complications from an infection on June 11, 2017. He was 71 years old. As a former Councilmember, his body lay in repose during a viewing in the John A. Wilson City Hall Building.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains distinct portions of records created by Jim Graham that is in three series. The first series concerns his work as Executive Director of the Whitman/Walker Clinic. These records include files of Jim Graham, constitution and by-laws for Whitman-Walker Clinic, correspondence, financial records, photographs, videocassettes, audio cassette tapes, executive meeting minutes, annual reports and other publications of the Whitman-Walker Clinic, publications and materials of other AIDS-related organizations, scrapbooks, newspaper articles, brochures, conference publications, property information, posters, and buttons related to Whitman-Walker events. The second series relates to Graham's work as a member of the District of Columbia Council and records of his work in the city. The third series contains additional Whitman/Walker materials, as well has some overlapping materials from Graham's tenure on City Council. A portion of the third series is personal material and other documents from Graham's early career as a lawyer, Senate aid, and university instructor. Additional donations were added to the collection in 2015 and 2018.
Collection Organization
Organized into three series: Jim Graham/Whitman Walker Clinic records, Jim Graham/D.C. Council records, and Personal papers
Related Materials
The Special Collections Research Center holds materials from multiple DC Councilmembers, as well as other local political figures--some were contemporaries of Jim Graham.
The Historical Society of Washington, D.C. also holds the Jim Graham Washingtoniana collection (MS 0834).
AIDS (Disease) -- Treatment -- United States; AIDS (Disease) -- Patients; AIDS (Disease) -- Prevention; Clinics; Gays -- Medical care; Gay men -- Washington (D.C.); Gays; Lesbians; City council members -- Washington (D.C.); Politicians; Law; Photographs; Audiocassettes; Videocassettes; Audiotapes; Scrapbooks; Graham, Jim; District of Columbia. City Council; Whitman-Walker Clinic; District of Columbia. City Council
- Jim Graham/Whitman-Walker Clinic records, 1973-1998; MS2013 Series 1
  Scope and Contents note
  The Jim Graham/Whitman-Walker Clinic, records include personal files of Jim Graham, constitution and by-laws for Whitman-Walker Clinic, correspondence, financial records, photographs, videocassettes, audio cassette tapes, executive meeting minutes, annual reports and other publications of the Whitman-Walker Clinic, publications and materials of other AIDS-related organizations, scrapbooks, newspaper articles, brochures, conference publications, property information, posters, and buttons related to Whitman-Walker events. This material collectively documents the foundation and growth of the Whitman-Walker Clinic under the direction of Clinic Administrator Jim Graham.
  The collection provides a wide range of information for those interested in the history of health services in Washington D.C., Gay organizations in Washington, D.C., and the growth of AIDS-related services in Washington, D.C.
  Jim Graham donated this collection in 1999 and 2007, with an additional donation in 2014.
  Arrangement
  Organized into eight subseries: Jim Graham, Executive files, Administrative files, Publications, Audio-visual materials, Oversized, Affiliated organizations, and Miscellaneous.
  - Jim Graham, 1982-1997; MS2013 Series 1 Subseries 1
    This subseries consists primarily of photographs. These images relate to Jim Graham's personal and professional work such as events with Whitman-Walker Clinic. The dates of the material range from 1981-98. Other highlights of this series include a biographical sketch of Jim Graham, correspondence, negatives and slides, speeches, and information concerning the travels of Jim Graham.
    - Committee on Economic Development Nomination, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence- Incoming/Outgoing, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Graham Biographical Summary and Other Information, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Graham, Jim Biographical Information, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - HHS Public Health Service, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - National Committee on National Health, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Notary Public Application, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Notebook, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Speeches, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Travel Itinerary, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Personal Photographs I, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Personal Photographs II, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Personal Photographs III, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Personal Photographs IV, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Speaking Engagements, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Personal Photographs V, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Personal Photographs VI, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Personal Photographs VII, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Personal Photographs VIII, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Personal Photographs IX, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Personal Photographs X, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Personal Photographs XI, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Personal Photographs XII, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Personal Photographs XIII, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Personal Photographs XIV, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Personal Photographs XV, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Personal Photographs XVI, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Personal Photographs XVII, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Personal Photographs XVIII, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Personal Photographs XIX, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Personal Photographs XX, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Personal Photographs XXI, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Personal Photographs XXII (WWC Halloween Party), Circa 1990s (Box 3A, Folder 1)
    - Personal Photographs XXIII, Circa 1990s (Box 3A, Folder 2)
    - Personal Photographs XXIV, 1997 (Box 3A, Folder 3)
    - Personal Photographs XXV, 1992 August (Box 3A, Folder 4)
    - Personal Photographs XXVI, 1997 December (Box 3A, Folder 5)
    - Contact Sheets, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Slides, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Negatives I, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Negatives II, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Executive files, 1981-1997; MS2013 Series 1 Subseries 2
    This subseries consists of items related to the executive board of the Whitman-Walker Clinic. The items date from 1981-97. The majority of items in this series are related to the Clinic's Board of Directors, and include memorandums and meeting minutes from board meetings. Other highlights include a Clinic mission statement, and the by-laws and articles of incorporation.
    - Articles of Incorporation, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Board Development, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Board of Directors I, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Board of Directors II, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Board of Directors III, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Board of Directors IV, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Board of Directors V, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Board of Directors VI, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Board of Directors VII, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Board of Directors- Ballots Concerning By-Law Amendment Submission to Volunteers, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Board of Directors Election Ballots, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Board of Directors and Executive Committee I, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Board of Directors and Executive Committee II, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Board of Directors Survey, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Board of Directors Survey II, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Board Lists- Program Directors, At-Large Directors, Client Representatives, Person Living with AIDS Seat, Non-Voting Ex-Officio, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Budget Report- 1990 Fiscal Year (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - By-Laws/Articles of Incorporation, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - By-Laws/Conflict of Interest Issues with D.C.General Hospital, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Customer Service Representative Office, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Democratic National Committee Platform Committee Hearing- National Gay and Lesbian Agenda, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Democratic National Convention Platform Committee, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Executive Committee- (Memorandum Dec.6, 1993, Sign-In Sheet July 11, 1994, Meeting Minutes July 11, 1994), 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Executive Committee Board of Directors Memorandums- November 1996, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Executive Committee Files, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes- AIDS Foundation, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes- AIDS Medical Services, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes- Notebook, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Management Committee Meeting Minutes, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Mark Hartmett-Board of Directors Executive Committee Meeting Minutes- Notebook, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Meeting Minutes, Long-term Goals, Memos, Mission Statements, Correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Mental Health Services, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Mission Statement, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Organizational Chart, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Policies Group- By-Laws, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Policies Group- Former Members of the Board of Directors and Officers, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Policies Group- Guidelines for Use of Facility, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Policy Manual, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Proposed By-Law Amendment, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Reorganization Proposal, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Ryan White Title III Competing Continuation Grant Application Progress Report, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Schwartz House- Charter and Records, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Steering Committee I, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Steering Committee II, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Study Group I, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Study Group II, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Viatrical Settlements, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Administrative files, 1980-1998; MS2013 Series 1 Subseries 3
    This subseries contains items related to the programs, activities, and policies of the Clinic. The dates of the materials range from 1980-98 Some of the items found in this series include papers related to numerous AIDS programs and education efforts of the Clinic, information regarding Whitman-Walker events, budget records and other financial papers, Clinic correspondence, newspaper articles, policy group records, and records related to Whitman-Walker offices and other property.
    - AAAS Presentation (American Association for the Advancement of Science), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Accessability Task Force I, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Accessability Task Force II, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Accessability Task Force III, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Accounting Policy, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Accounts Receivable Aging Schedule, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - ADAP Information, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Addiction Services, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Addictions Service Quarter, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Ad-Hoc Committee Visual Display, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Administrator, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Adoption of PBC Seal I, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Adoption of PBC Seal II, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Advisory Screening Committee, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Affiliation Agreement Between George Washington University and the Whitman-Walker Clinic, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Agreement Between the Whitman-Walker Clinic and Darrel Downing Rippeteau Architects, P.C., undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - AHA (Agency for HIV/AIDS), undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - AIDS Action Board Handbook, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - AIDS Action Council I, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - AIDS Action Council II, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - AIDS Awareness Publications, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - AIDSCAP Meeting, September 30, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - AIDS Committee I, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - AIDS Committee II, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - AIDS Committee III, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - AIDS Committee IV, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - AIDS Committee V, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - AIDS Education Brochure, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - AIDS Education Fund I, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - AIDS Education Fund II, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - AIDS Education Fund III, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - AIDS Education Funding Proposal, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - AIDS Education Project Volunteer Training Manual, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - AIDS Education Task Force, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - AIDS Evaluation Unit, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - AIDS Foundation, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - AIDS Foundation Requests, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - AIDS Numbers D.C.I, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - AIDS Numbers in D.C.II, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - AIDS Program Steering Committee Meeting Minutes, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - AIDS Ride Agreement I, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - AIDS Ride Agreement II, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - AIDS Risk Reduction/Education, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - AIDS Services, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - AIDS Services Delivery, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - AIDS Study Group, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - AIDS Walk, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - AIDS Walk I, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - AIDS Walk II, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - AIDS Walk, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - AIDS Walk Foundation Members, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - AIDS Walk Planning, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - AIDS Walk Speech given by Jim Graham, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - AIDS Walk Spending Plans, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - AIDS Walk Sponsors Luncheon, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - AIDS Walk Washington-I, August 7, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - AIDS Walk Washington-II, August 7, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - AIDS Walk Washington Program, May 15, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - AIDS Walk Washington Program/ Including HIV/AIDS Directory and Calendar, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Alcohol Services Contracts, 1983-1984 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Alliance for Justice, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Alternative and Holistic Health Care, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Anacostia/Congress Heights Partnership, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Annual Meeting Board of Directors, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Annual Report List, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - AP (AIDS Program) Reorganization, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - AP (AIDS Program) Steering Committee, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Application for Employment at the Whitman-Walker Clinic- Blank, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Appointment to Mayor's Blue Ribbon Panel on Health Care Reform, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Archival Lists- Various Committees and Programs, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Area Neighborhood Commission Chair List, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Arent Fox, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Articles R.C.Ryan, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - ASO (AIDS Service Organizations) Contracts, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Audit- Austin Center, December, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Audit- D.C., December, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Audit - D.C. General Hospital Response to the 1995-1996 Fiscal Year, Management Letter, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Audit- DHS, December, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Audit- Haymaker, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Baker, C. and Lovelace, Dr., undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Barry Fund-raising, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Beech Street Foundation, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Benefit Performance- Kiss of the Spider Woman, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Big 6 Meeting- HRs/CFOs/EDs, December 2-3, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Blue Cross, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Board Advisory Committees, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Board Annual Meeting, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Board Nominations, Fall, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Bonuses, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Bross, Dan- Correspondence, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Budget, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Budget, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Budget, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Budget, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Budget, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Budget Correspondence, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Budget- Fiscal Year, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Budget- Fiscal Year, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Budget- Fiscal Year, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Budget- Fiscal Year, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Budget- Fiscal Year, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Budget Proposal- Fiscal Year, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Budget Proposal- Fiscal Year, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Budget vs. Actual- October, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Budget vs. Actual- December, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Budget vs. Actual- May, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Bureau of Alcoholism Treatment, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)